General
장군
They retreated too quickly
놈들이 너무 빨리 퇴각하여
Didn't catch them all
다 붙잡진 못했습니다
Prince of Jin
진왕
That rabbit emperor in the south
남쪽의 그 토끼 황제가
Has raised a wolf
늑대 새끼를 키웠구나
Just lost some tents
군장막을 좀 손실했을 뿐이에요
General Shi's fifty thousand troops
장군의 병력은 5만이라
No matter how he schemes
그놈이 아무리 기습해봤자
It's just
살짝
A breeze brushing fur
생채기 내는 정도 아니겠어요
What do you know?
자네가 뭘 알아
When two armies fight
전쟁에 있어서
It's all about momentum
관건은 사기야
The Xuan people's arrows
선나라인들 화살은
Have almost all been used on the refugees
난민한테 거의 다 써버렸어
Call the craftsmen
장인들이 만든
The finished catapults
투석기를 가져와
At dawn
날이 밝으면
Send two units
두 부대가 번갈아
To attack the city in rotation
공성할 것이야
On the other side
다른 한쪽도
Work faster too
빨리 속도 내라고 해
Yes
네
Send people out of the city
사람을 성 밖에 내보내
To recover arrows as much as possible
화살을 최대한 회수해
At the same time
동시에
Open the southern grain storehouse
성남 곡창을 열어
Reward our troops for the successful raid
기습의 성공을 치하하고
Have the soldiers
장병들과 함께
Celebrate together
경축해라
Yes
네
This General Zhu
주 장군은
Truly has the courage of a bear and tiger
역시나 담대해
I saw in the Wuzhao camp
오노 군영에서
Flames reaching the sky
타오르는 불길을 보며
Truly satisfying
얼마나 통쾌했는지 몰라
Pity
근데
Only good food
좋은 음식만 있고
No wine
술이 없어서 아쉬워
I think
이게 어쩌면
This meal is like a last meal
마지막 식사일 수도 있어
Zhu Yuanzhi showed off
주원지가 도발했으니
Won't the Wuzhao retaliate?
오노가 복수 안 하겠어
Maybe they'll launch a full attack tonight
오늘 밤에라도 총공격할지 누가 알아
Lately I
전 요즘
Can't sleep well
잠도 잘 못 자요
Always hear
자꾸 툭툭하는
Thumping sounds
소리가 들리며
Always dream of Wuzhao warhorses
제가 오노의 말발굽에
Trampling down on me
밟히는 꿈을 꿉니다
Shut up and eat
입 다물고 밥이나 먹어
Stop thinking about this and that
없는 일로
Scaring yourself
스스로 겁주지 말고
Although we've repelled the enemy
적이 철수했으나
But arrows are exhausted
우린 화살이 바닥났고
All kinds of weapons and traps
함정과 무기도
Are also severely depleted
소모가 큽니다
Also
그리고
Need to immediately assign people
빨리 인력을 동원해
To urgently repair the city walls
성벽을 보수해야 합니다
How many men do we have left?
우리 군은 얼마 남았어
Heavy casualties
사상자가 많아서
Now only about two thousand can still fight
싸울 수 있는 병력은 2천 여명입니다
If the Wuzhao attack again
오노가 또 공격해 오면
At most we can
기껏해야 이틀을
Hold for two days
버틸 수 있어요
Report
아룁니다
There's an army to the south
성남 쪽에서
Approaching us
군대가 다가오고 있습니다
They don't look like Wuzhao
오노 병사는 아닌 것 같아요
Chen Ying's reinforcements have arrived
진응의 원군인가
Let's go take a look
나가 보자
Who goes there?
누구냐
I'm Liu Dadao
유대도라 하오
Commander of Yong'an Garrison's Left Army
영안 수위 좌군 통령이오
These
이 사람들은
Are all the lords of northern fortresses
북지의 작은 성 영주들이오
Zhang, Huang, Liu, Li
장 씨 황 씨 유 씨 이 씨
The four great families
4대 가족도
Have also come
함께 왔소
Although we're in the north
우리 몸은 북지에 있지만
In our hearts
마음은
We always recognize the Xuan on this flag
이 깃발에 적힌 선자만 따르오
Everyone heard the royal army is trapped in Yiyang
선나라 군이 익양에서 공격받는다는 소식을 듣고
Specially led the northern volunteer army
의병을 거느리고
To come and help
도우러 왔소
Great Xuan's old subjects
선나라 옛 백성들
Willing to die for Great Xuan
선나라를 위해 목숨 바치겠습니다
It's reinforcements
원군이에요
Our reinforcements
우리 군 원군이 왔어요
Your Highness
전하
Look
보십시오